Guide to the Sydney Ahlstrom Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Sydney Ahlstrom Papers
1931-1988
RG 83
Yale University Divinity School Library
20
(49 boxes)
The papers document Ahlstrom's professional career, his writings, lectures, courses taught at Yale, his extensive participation in scholarly and church-related organizations. Conditions at Yale and in New Haven during the turbulent years of the late 1960s and early 1970s are well documented. Correspondence documents his friendships, family life, and professional affairs, revealing his opinions on a wide range of issues, his sense of humor and warm personality. The collection includes material relating to the many institutions, organizations, committees, and projects with which Ahlstrom was involved, particularly in the areas of Lutheranism, higher education and American religious history. Sydney E. Ahlstrom was born in Cokato, Minnesota on December 16, 1919. He taught at Yale from 1954 to 1984. He was the author of several notable books on religion in America. Ahlstrom held prominent positions on various boards and organizations, including the Editorial Board of the Complete Works of Jonathan Edwards, the American Studies Program and Religious Studies Department at Yale, and the American Society of Church History. Ahlstrom died in New Haven in 1984.
Ahlstrom, Sydney E., 1919-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Ahlstrom,
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1919 Dec 16 Sydney Eckman Ahlstrom born in Cokato, Minnesota, son of Joseph T. and Selma Eckman Ahlstrom
1941 B.A. Gustavus Adolphus College
1942-1946 U.S. Army, Captain
1946 Instructor in history, Gustavus Adolphus M.A. University of Minnesota
1948-1952 Teaching fellow and history tutor, Harvard University
1951-1952 Fulbright fellow, University of Strasbourg, France
1952 Faculty member, Salzburg Seminar in American Studies, Austria Ph.D. Harvard, Instructor in history
1953 Aug 8 Married Nancy Ethel Alexander (Children: J. Alexander, b. 1954; Promise, b. 1955; Constance, b. 1957; Sydney, b. 1960)
1954 Fellow, Branford College, Yale Assistant Professor of Modern Church History and American History, Yale University The Harvard Divinity School published (co-author)
1957 Lutheran World Federation lecturer in various countries of Europe
1960 Associate Professor, Yale
1961 The Shaping of American Religion published (co-author)
1962 Spring Visiting Professor, Princeton University The American Protestant Encounter with World Religions (Brewer Lectures, Beloit College) published
1964 Full Professor, Yale
1964-1965 Research in Paris, France
1965 Calvinism and the Political Order published (co-author)
1967-1971 Chair, American Studies Program, Yale
1967 Rauschenbusch Lecturer, Colgate Rochester Divinity School
1967 Theology in America published
1970-1971 Research in Munich, Germany
1972 Summer Visiting Professor, Kyoto Summer Seminar in American Studies, Japan
1972 A Religious History of the American People published
1972-1973 Director of Graduate Studies, Religious Studies Department, Yale
1973 National Book Award Recipient
1973 Summer Scholar-in-Resident, Aspen Institute of Humanistic Studies, Colorado Chair, Consulting Committee on the National Bicentenary of the Lutheran Church in America
1973-1974 Chair, American Studies Program, Yale
1974 Brotherhood Award of the National Council of Christians and Jews
1975 Visiting Lecturer at universities and professional conferences in Australia and New Zealand
1975 Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters, Upsala College, New Jersey
1975 President, American Society of Church History
1976 Honorary Doctor of Letters, Susquehanna University
1976 Religious Dilemmas of Nationhood published (editor)
1978 Rockefeller Fellowship for research on Romanticism
1979 Samuel Knight Professor of American History and Modern Religious History, Yale
1979 The Christian Century Award for the Decade's Most Outstanding Book on Religion
1984 Died in New Haven, Connecticut
Member, Editorial Board of the Complete Works of Jonathan Edwards
Member, Board of Trustees of Gustavus Adolphus
Elected Member, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1978
Elected Corresponding Member, Massachusetts Historical Society, 1977
Scope and Contents
These papers document in a very thorough way Ahlstrom's professional career, his writings, lectures, courses taught at Yale, his extensive participation in scholarly and church-related organizations. Conditions at Yale and in New Haven during the turbulent years of the late 1960s and early 1970s are well documented. A sampling of material has been preserved to document Ahlstrom's renowned personality, his sense of humor, curiosity, and wide-ranging interests.
A small section of family correspondence in Series I provides a view into Ahlstrom's Minnesota connections and warm family relationships. General correspondence dating from 1946 to 1979 includes letters to and from friends, colleagues, editors, publishers, and church representatives. Correspondents include Yale colleagues James Gustafson, Hans Frei, and Julian Hartt, as well as Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., Paul Ramsey, Samuel H. Miller, Robert Handy, Bruce Kuklick, and others. Substantive letters deal not only with academic and professional affairs, but also document Ahlstrom's opinions on a wide range of issues, his friendships, and family life. Revealing of strongly held convictions are letters such as one written to J.B. Buckley, manager of the Yellow Cab Company in New Haven, which protests against the unjust treatment of a poor black family by a cabdriver in a scene witnessed by Ahlstrom. The section of correspondence with students provides insight into Ahlstrom's interaction with his students. Correspondence related to Ahlstrom's writings, lecture appearances, and other specific events or activities can also be found in Series II, III and VI.
Series II, Committees and Projects, contains correspondence and other material related to the many institutions, organizations, committees, and projects with which Ahlstrom was involved. Ahlstrom's career-long interests and involvement in Lutheranism, higher education, and American religious history are documented, as well as his participation in a variety of short-term, specific projects.
The Writings of Series III constitute the bulk of this collection. Articles and unpublished papers, contributions to booklength works, letters to editors, book reviews by Ahlstrom and documentation related to his booklength works are included. Sermons and lectures delivered by Ahlstrom are filed with supporting documentation in Series VI.
Series IV, Course-related Material, includes primarily lecture notes, syllabi, exams, and reading lists. These materials date from 1946 to 1984. Material from his popular interdepartmental American Church History Survey course includes more than 2 1/2 boxes of lecture notes of one word per page. His deteriorating health prevented him from reading long pages of lecture notes. Moreover, his delivery was personal and conversational, and the system of one-word-per-page best served his lecturing style.
Ahlstrom was an inveterate collector of newspaper clippings, cartoons, concert programs, articles, offprints, and anything else that happened to touch upon one of his varied interests. The Collected Material of Series V represents a sampling of the mass of such materials present in Ahlstrom's offices at the time of his death. The largest section of material retained in this Series, collected material related to the fields of history, religion, and education, includes primarily offprints and articles sent to Ahlstrom by his colleagues, friends, and former students.
Series VI, Biographical Documentation, traces Ahlstrom's activities other than his long-term committee and project involvements and his regular teaching commitments at Yale. The series primarily documents one-time events such as conferences, lectures, seminars, awards, etc. Included are many holograph and typescript texts for Ahlstrom's various guest lecture appearances, sermons, and chapel talks dating from his graduation from Gustavus Adolphus until his death in 1984. Ahlstrom was much in demand as a lecturer, and his speaking engagements took him all over the country and as far as Japan and Australia. Other events that highlight his extra-curricular life include his involvement with 19 other Lutheran scholars in a statement supporting John F. Kennedy's 1960 presidential election and a Religion in America television show in 1974. "In Memory of Ahlstrom," by George Lindbeck and a journal tribute are also included. The series ends with miscellaneous material including Ahlstrom's own bibliographies and curriculum vitae.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Committees and Projects
III. Writings
IV. Course-related Material
V. Collected Material
VI. Biographical Documentation
Religious education; Universities and colleges -- Religion; United States -- Religion; Educators; Ahlstrom, Sydney E., 1919-; Frei, Hans W.; Gustafson, James M., 1925-; Handy, Robert T., 1918-2009; Hartt, Julian Norris, 1911-; Kuklick, Bruce, 1941-; Miller, Samuel Howard, 1900-1968; Ramsey, Paul; American Society of Church History; Yale University
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into three sections:
  Family Correspondence
  General Correspondence
  Student Correspondence
  - Family Correspondence
    - J. Millard Ahlstrom (brother), 1955-1975, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Selma Eckman Ahlstrom (mother), 1962, 1963, 1980, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Family circular letters, 1971, 1973-1975, 1978, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3-15)
    - Correspondence, 1966 -1970 Jun (Box 2, Folder 16-30)
    - Correspondence, 1970 Jul-1975 Oct (Box 3, Folder 31-43)
    - Correspondence, 1975 Nov-1979 (Box 4, Folder 44-55)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Student Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1956-1984, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 57-68)
- Committees and Projects, Series II
  This material is arranged alphabetically by title of the committee or project. One section is designated Lutheran Church in America and includes committees and projects affiliated with the LCA.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - American Antiquarian Society, 1979, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - American Historical Society, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - American Quarterly, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - American Society of Church History, 1956-1979, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 70-79)
  - American Studies Program - Chair, 1967-1974 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Armory Street Committee, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Branford College, 1955-1973 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Comparative Religious History, 1971-1973 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Coordinating Committee for the Study of Religion, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Coronet Instructional Films: Religious Freedom in America's Beginning, 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Dialog, 1961-1975 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Educational Psychology and Measurements (Box 7, Folder 88-90)
  - Friends of American Art, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 91-92)
  - Gustavus Adolphus Board of Trustees, 1970-1976 (Box 7, Folder 93-94)
  - Library of Protestant Thought, 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 95-96)
  - Library of Protestant Thought, 1964-1971, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 97-100)
  - Lutheran Church in America: Commission on Church Papers, 1962-1967, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Lutheran Church in America: Commission on the Ministry, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Lutheran Church in America: Consulting Committee on the U.S. Bicentenary, 1973-1976, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 103-108)
  - Lutheran Church in America: Examining Committee, 1963-1970, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 109-110)
  - Lutheran Church in America: Film Committee of the Consulting Committee on the U.S. Bicentenary, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Lutheran Church in America: Task Force on New England Synod Archives, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1977-1978, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ: Commission on Higher Education, 1962-1966 (Box 9, Folder 114-116)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1974-1978 (Box 9, Folder 117-118)
  - National Humanities Institute, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 119)
  - National Workshop on Christian-Jewish Relations, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 120)
  - New England American Studies Association, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - New Haven Theological Discussion Group, 1969, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - University Lutheran Association, 1957-1966, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - World Council of Churches: Commission on Faith and Order, 1958-1963 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - The Works of Jonathan Edwards, 1969-1983 (Box 10, Folder 124-125)
  - Yale College Faculty Committee on Teaching and Learning, 1970-1975 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Yale Divinity School Tenure Committee, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Yale Divinity School Committee on Practical Theology, 1972-1976 (Box 10, Folder 127-128)
- Writings, Series III
  This series is divided into six sections:
  1. Articles and Unpublished Papers are arranged alphabetically by title with dates indicated when available.
  2. Contributions/Chapters are arranged chronologically.
  3. Forewords and Introductions are arranged chronologically.
  4. Letters to the Editor are arranged chronologically within one folder.
  5. Book Reviews by Ahlstrom are arranged chronologically.
  6. Booklength Works are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Articles and Unpublished Papers
    - Across the Atlantic, Lutheran Herald, 1957 Sep 17 (Box 11, Folder 129)
    - Albert Bushnell Hart, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 130-131)
    - The American National Faith, The Changing Nature of America's Civil Religion, An Occasional Paper/The Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 132)
    - The American Frontier and the Protestant Missionary Response, The Student World, 1960 Spr (Box 11, Folder 133)
    - The American Protestant Encounter with World Religions, The Brewer Lectures, 1962 Oct (Box 11, Folder 133)
    - The Americanization of Christianity, Frontiers, 1960 Jan (Box 11, Folder 134)
    - Den Amerikanska kristenhetens kris, Var Losen, 1968 Jun (Box 11, Folder 134)
    - American Religion and the Lutheran Church (proposed paper), 1961-1966 (Box 11, Folder 135)
    - American Religious Values and the Future of America, 1976? (Box 11, Folder 136)
    - Annuit Coeptis: America as the Elect Nation, The Rise and Decline of a Patriotic Tradition (Box 11, Folder 137)
    - Barth, Wittgenstein, and St. Paul, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 137)
    - A Bibliography of American Religious History, American Studies: An International Newsletter, 1972 Fall (Box 11, Folder 138)
    - Christianity and Scientific Philosophy (Box 11, Folder 139)
    - The Church and the American Way (Box 11, Folder 139)
    - Civil Religion, History of American Christianity, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 140)
    - Closing the Ranks, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 140)
    - Continental Influence on American Christian Thought Since World War I, Church History, 1958 Sep (Box 11, Folder 141)
    - The Dilemmas of American Pluralism, Religion and the Dilemmas of Nationhood, U.S. Bicentennial Series of the Knubel-Miller-Greever Lectures, Lutheran Church in America, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 142)
    - Diversity in Religion as a Force for Liberty, The American Philosophical Society Lectures, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 143)
    - Eliot, the Tutor and Fireman, Harvard Alumni Bulletin, 1949 Mar 12 (Box 11, Folder 144)
    - E Pluribus Unum: Religious Pluralism and the American Ideal, Soundings, 1978 Fall (Box 12, Folder 144)
    - Francis Ellingwood Abbot and the Free Religious Association, Proceedings of the Unitarian Historical Society, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 145)
    - Francis Greenwood Peabody, Dictionary of American Biography, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 145)
    - First Mark of a Church College, Journal of the Association of Lutheran College Faculties, 1959 Dec (Box 12, Folder 146)
    - God is Not a Junkman, The Lutheran Companion, 1957 Feb 20 (Box 12, Folder 147)
    - The Gospel in Our Age, The Christian Century, 1951 Jan 3 (Box 12, Folder 147)
    - Historical Reflections on the Ethics of Volkerwanderugen (Box 12, Folder 148)
    - H. Richard Niebuhr's Place in American Thought, Christianity and Crisis, 1963 Nov 25 (Box 12, Folder 149)
    - H. Richard Niebuhr, Dialog, 1963 Jan 1 (Box 12, Folder 149)
    - Internal Threats to American Civilization (prepared for Franco-American Conference, sponsored by World Peace Federation), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 150)
    - It is for the Living... Some Centennial Reflections, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 151)
    - Josiah Royce and the Triumph of Idealism in American Philosophy (proposed paper), 1954 (Box 12, Folder 151)
    - The Levels of Religious Revival, Confluence, 1955 Apr (Box 12, Folder 152)
    - The Liturgical Movement and American Lutheranism, UNA SANCTA, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 152)
    - Lord Acton's Famous Remark, New York Times, 1974 Mar 13 (Box 12, Folder 153)
    - The Lutheran Church and American Culture, The Lutheran Quarterly, 1957 Nov (Box 12, Folder 154)
    - The Lutheran Renaissance and the Lutheran Teacher, Lutheran Faculty, 1955 May (Box 12, Folder 154)
    - Montreal 1963 as Event and Taskmaster, Signs and Times, and Lutheran World, 1963 Dec, 1964 Jan (Box 12, Folder 155)
    - Montreal 1963- Ereignis und Prufung, Lutherische Rundschau, 1964 Jan (Box 12, Folder 155)
    - The Moral and Theological Revolution of the 1960s and Its Implications for American Religious Historiography, The State of American History, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 156)
    - The National Faith, Yale Alumni Magazine, 1973 Jan (Box 12, Folder 157)
    - The National Faith in the 1970s (presented at Worldview Conference on Patriotism), n.d.
    - National Trauma and Changing Religious Values, Daedalus, 1978 Winter (Box 12, Folder 158-159)
    - The Nature of Lutheran Witness, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 160)
    - Neo-Evangelism and the Puritan Heritage in America, The Evangelical Resurgence, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 161-162)
    - Neo-Orthodoxy Demythologized, The Christian Century, 1957 May 22 (Box 13, Folder 163)
    - The New Industrial Society and the Church, Lutheran World, 1958 Mar (Box 13, Folder 163)
    - The New Puritanism, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 164-165)
    - Night Thoughts on the Curriculum, Signs and Times, 1961 Apr 20 (Box 13, Folder 166)
    - Norman Vincent Peale, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 166)
    - On the Purpose and Significance of Regional Study With Special Reference to New England (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - The Pieties of Usefulness, Stetson University Bulletin, 1957 Jul (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - The Problem of the History of Religion in America, Church History, 1970 Jun, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 168)
    - Prot. Theologie, Religion in Geschichte und Gegenwart, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 168)
    - The Radical Turn in Theology and Ethics: Why It Occured in the 60s, The Annals of American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1970 Jan (Box 13, Folder 169)
    - Ralph Waldo Emerson and the American Transcendentalists (drafts), 1980 (Box 13, Folder 170-172)
    - Ralph Waldo Emerson and the American Transcendentalists (drafts), 1980 (Box 14, Folder 173-176)
    - Rediscovering America, The Lutheran, 1974 Sep 18 (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - Reflections on Religion, Nature, and the Exploitative Mentality (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - Religion in America and the Phantoms of National Character: The Search for a Common Theme (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - Religion and Democracy in America (outline), 1963 (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - Religion and Presidential Politics, Signs and Times, 1960 Oct 10 (Box 14, Folder 178)
    - Religion, Revolution and the Rise of Modern Nationalism, Church History, 1975 Dec (Box 14, Folder 178)
    - The Religious Dimensions of American Aspirations, The Review of Politics, 1976 Jul (Box 14, Folder 179)
    - Religious Toleration in Maryland to 1650 (Box 14, Folder 179)
    - Requiem for Patriotic Piety, Worldview, 1972 Aug (Box 14, Folder 179)
    - Retrospect (proposed paper?), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 180)
    - Rifts in the Evangelical United Front, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 181)
    - The Rise and Flowering of the Puritan Spirit (Box 14, Folder 181)
    - The Romantic Religious Revolution and the Dilemmas of Religious History, Church History, 1977 Jun (Box 14, Folder 182)
    - Romanticism as a Religious Revolution (abridged version of Haverford lectures on Romanticism), 1971 (Box 14, Folder 182)
    - The Saybrook Platform, Bulletin of the Congregational Library, 1959 Oct (Box 14, Folder 182)
    - Scottish Philosophy and American Theology, Church History, 1955 Sep (Box 14, Folder 183)
    - Some Thoughts on the Bicentennial, LCA publication, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 184)
    - Soren Kierkegaard, The Lutheran Companion, 1957 Nov 20 (Box 14, Folder 184)
    - Studying America and American Studies at Yale, Ventures, and American Quarterly, 1969 Spring, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 184)
    - Szabadsagunk az egyhaz megreformalasara, Lelkipasztor, 1957 Jun (Box 15, Folder 185)
    - Theology and the Present Day Revival, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1960 Nov (Box 15, Folder 185)
    - Thomas Hooker-Puritanism and Democratic Citizenship, Church History, 1963 Dec (Box 15, Folder 186)
    - Toward the Idea of a Church College, The Christian Scholar, 1960 Mar (Box 15, Folder 187)
    - Toward a Portrait of John Adams as a Young Man, 1947 Feb (Box 15, Folder 188)
    - Tradition in Transit and Tension, Encounter, 1959 Summer (Box 15, Folder 188-189)
    - An Unfortunate Choice, The Lutheran Companion, 1960 Jan 27 (Box 15, Folder 190)
    - Unity, A Lutheran Imperative, The Lutheran Outlook, 1946 Feb (Box 15, Folder 190)
    - What's Lutheran About Higher Education? - A Critique, LCA Papers and Proceedings, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 190)
    - Miscellaneous Papers and Notes (Box 15, Folder 191)
  - Contributions/Chapters
    - The Middle Period (1840-80), The Harvard Divinity School, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 192)
    - Facing the New World: Augustana and the American Challenge, Centennial Essays: Augustana Lutheran Church 1860-1960, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 192)
    - Samuel Hopkins, Encyclopedia Britannica, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 193)
    - Horace Bushnell, Encyclopedia Britannica, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 194)
    - Horace Bushnell, A Handbook of Christian Theologians, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 195)
    - Theology in America: A Historical Survey, The Shaping of American Religion, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 196)
    - The Puritan Ethic and the Spirit of American Democracy, Calvinism and the Political Order, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 197)
    - Mary Baker Eddy, Notable American Women, 1607-1950, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 198-200)
    - Symposium on the Wolf Paper, Gettysburgiana Bulletin, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 201)
    - Religion, Revolution and the Rise of Modern Nationalism, Mead Festschift, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 202-203)
    - From Puritansim to Evangelicalism: A Critical Perspective, The Evangelicals, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 204)
    - The Religious Dimensions of American Aspirations, An Almost Chosen People, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 204)
    - Theodore Parker, Religious Thought in the 19th Century, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 205)
    - Ministry from the Placid Decade to the Present, The Ministry in Historical Perspectives, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 206)
  - Forewords and Introductions
    - Transcendentalism in New England, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 207-208)
    - Piety Vs. Moralism: The Passing of New England Theology, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 209)